<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nutr Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nutr Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1752</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nutd</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">101566341</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nutrition &amp; Diabetes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-4052</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5916923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC5916923.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">5916923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">5916923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29695709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41387-018-0033-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">33</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Longitudinal association between egg consumption and the risk of cardiovascular disease: interaction with type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiyoung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Min-Jeong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="OY">Oh Yoen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4681-1584</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="K">Kyong</given-names></name><address><phone>+82-53-810-2879</phone><email>kypark@ynu.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 4447</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413028.c</institution-id><institution>Department of Food and Nutrition, </institution><institution>Yeungnam University, </institution></institution-wrap>Gyeongsan, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0840 2678</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.222754.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health Sciences, BK21PLUS Program in Embodiment: Health-Society Interaction, Graduate School, </institution><institution>Korea University, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2218 7142</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.255166.3</institution-id><institution>Department of Food Science and Nutrition, </institution><institution>Dong-A University, </institution></institution-wrap>Busan, Republic of Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">308399</issue-id><elocation-id>20</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>25</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2018-04-28 05:21:04.450"><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2018</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41387_2018_Article_33.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background/objectives</title><p id="Par1">It remains unclear if high egg consumption has beneficial or adverse effects on cardiometabolic health. The present study prospectively evaluated the longitudinal association between egg-consumption levels and incident cardiovascular disease (CVD) among Korean adults.</p></sec><sec><title>Subjects/methods</title><p id="Par2">We conducted a prospective cohort study of 9248 Korean adults aged 40–69 years without CVD or cancer at the baseline from the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study, Ansung–Ansan cohort, South Korea. The egg intake of the participants was estimated using a validated semiquantitative food frequency questionnaire at the baseline and the second follow-up examination and categorized into quartiles. CVD cases were identified using biennial questionnaires and confirmed through repeated in-depth personal interviews. Hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) were analyzed using Cox proportional hazard regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">During the average follow-up of 7.3 years, 570 cases of CVD were newly diagnosed. After adjusting for multiple confounding variables, egg-intake levels were not associated with CVD incidence (HR: 1.14, 95% CI: 0.87–1.49, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend: 0.7). However, the association was modified by type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) status. Egg consumption was significantly associated with an increased risk for incident CVD among participants with T2DM; individuals with the highest egg intake (4.2 ± 0.04 eggs/week) had a 2.8 times higher incidence of CVD (HR: 2.81, 95% CI: 1.25–6.30, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend: 0.02) than those with the lowest egg intake (0.1 ± 0.02 eggs/week). However, no association was observed among individuals without T2DM (HR: 1.03, 95% CI: 0.77–1.38, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend: 0.8).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Higher egg consumption may increase the risk for CVD in Korean patients with T2DM. Our findings provide a basis for the development of an optimal dietary cholesterol intake guideline for the Korean population.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Although eggs are an affordable and healthy source of high-quality protein and micronutrients (e.g., essential fatty acids, antioxidants, vitamins, and minerals)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, the role of egg consumption with regard to increasing the risk for cardiovascular disease (CVD) and diabetes has been debated for decades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, mainly due to eggs’ high content of dietary cholesterol (200–250 mg per middle-sized egg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Observational studies and randomized controlled trials (RCT) have reported conflicting data on the effect of egg consumption on lipid profiles and cardiometabolic health, with some showing beneficial and others adverse effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In a recent systematic review, Richard et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> reported that consuming 1–2 eggs per day for 12 weeks did not adversely affect some CVD risk factors, including plasma concentrations of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), glucose, and inflammation markers (TNF-α and IL-6) among patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). However, a meta-analysis of prospective studies suggested that egg consumption significantly increased the risk of CVD morbidity in patients with T2DM, while the egg-consumption level was not associated with an increased risk for CVD and cardiac mortality in the general population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">To date, data on the association between dietary cholesterol intake and CVD risk were mainly reported in the United States (US) and the countries of the European Union (EU). The results of these studies might therefore not be suitable evidence for developing dietary guidelines for populations other than those of the US and the EU. There is limited information on the association between the level of egg consumption and the risk for cardiometabolic disease in the Korean population, whose average cholesterol intake is lower than that of Western populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">In this study, we examined the association between egg-consumption levels and CVD incidence in Korea, using the data set of a longitudinal cohort of the Ansung–Ansan region. Moreover, we tested whether the association was modified by the presence of T2DM.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par9">This study used data of the Ansung–Ansan cohort, obtained from the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study. The details and design of the survey method have been described elsewhere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Briefly, the Ansung–Ansan cohort study was conducted among the residents of the Ansan (urban) and Ansung (rural) areas of the Gyeonggi Province, Republic of Korea. The baseline survey was performed in 2001–2002 and involved 10030 adults aged 40–69 years; the follow-up study has been conducted every 2 years thereafter. During follow-up, data on demographics, lifestyle, health examinations and diagnostic records, metabolic indicators, and disease incidence have been collected. The overall data collection and management were handled by a trained investigator based on a standardized protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">Among the participants of the Ansung–Ansan cohort-based survey, those with a previous diagnosis of cancer or CVD and the related diseases, and those taking drugs for these diseases were excluded from this study (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 498). Participants with a total energy intake of &lt;2092 (500 kcal) or &gt;20920 (5000 kcal) kJ/d (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 162)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> and those who did not have available data on egg consumption or diabetes diagnosis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 122) were also excluded. Finally, 9248 participants were included in the analysis (Supplementary Figure <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">Informed consent was obtained from all participants included in the study, and the study was approved by the ethics committees of the Korean Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (IRB number: KU-IRB-15-EX-256-A-1) and Yeungnam University (IRB number: 7002016-E-2016-003).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Dietary assessment</title><p id="Par12">Dietary information, including that on egg consumption, was obtained from the results of the baseline (2001–2002) and second follow-up (2005–2006) surveys, using a semiquantitative food frequency questionnaire (SQFFQ) consisting of 106 food items. The details regarding the validity of the SQFFQ have been described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Briefly, the validity of the SQFFQ was examined by comparing 12-day dietary records. The deattenuated age-adjusted, sex-adjusted, and energyintake-adjusted correlation coefficients ranged between 0.23 and 0.64. The reproducibility of the SQFFQ was acceptable, showing a mean correlation coefficient between two SQFFQs conducted with a 1-year interval of 0.45 for all nutrient intakes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Each item of the SQFFQ offers nine response options for food frequency (almost never, once/month, 2–3 times/month, 1–2 times/week, 3–4 times/week, 5–6 times/week, once/day, twice/day, and thrice/day) and three response options for portion size (0.5 times the reference, the reference, and 1.5–2 times the reference).</p><p id="Par13">Weighted food frequencies were calculated, considering both frequency and portion-size responses; finally, we used the mean values of the weighted food frequencies reported at the baseline, and the second follow-up to minimize the misclassification of dietary information. The total vegetable intake frequency was obtained by summating the overall servings of 15 kinds of vegetables, including Chinese cabbage, spinach, pepper leaves, lettuce, perilla leaves, balloon flower roots, carrots, crown daisies, bean sprouts, bracken, aged amber, green peppers, cucumbers, onions, and oyster mushrooms except for kimchi. Similarly, the total fruit intake frequency was calculated by determining the sum of the overall servings of 11 types of fruits, including strawberries, persimmons, mandarins, oranges, oriental melons, watermelons, pears, apples, bananas, peaches, and grapes. Furthermore, the intake frequency of red meat was determined by obtaining the overall servings of beef and pork, excluding other processed meats.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>General participant characteristics, anthropometric measurements, and biochemical variables</title><p id="Par14">Demographic and lifestyle data of the participants, including age, sex, area of residence, educational level, monthly household income, smoking status, alcohol consumption, physical activity level, as well as medical and family history of diseases, were collected by trained investigators using a questionnaire. Educational level was categorized into elementary school or lower, middle school, high school, and college graduate or higher. Monthly household income was divided into &lt;1 million Korean Republic Won (KRW), 1–&lt;2 million KRW, 2–&lt;4 million KRW, and ≥4 million KRW. Smoking status was determined by calculating the pack-year and converting the number of cigarettes smoked/day to the number of packs consumed. For alcohol consumption, we used the weekly intake frequency (glasses/week), and the physical activity level was determined using the metabolic equivalent of task (MET-hours/week) by calculating the time spent on exercise/week and assigning a weight based on exercise intensity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The MET scores of the participants were classified as &lt;20, 20–&lt;40, and ≥40 MET-hours/week. Weight and height of the participants were obtained by trained technicians. The body mass index (BMI) was calculated by dividing the body weight in kilograms by the square of the height in meters. The World Health Organization’s BMI standard for Asian populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> was used to classify the participants as underweight, normal weight, overweight, and obese. Biomarkers in blood (e.g., total cholesterol, LDL-C, HDL-C, and triglyceride) were determined by an organization using a standardized protocol.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Assessment of cardiovascular disease incidence</title><p id="Par15">Incident CVD cases were identified through biennial questionnaires, and all reported cases were confirmed by trained staff during personal interviews. CVD incidence was defined as newly diagnosed cases of myocardial infarction, coronary artery disease, cerebrovascular diseases, or based on taking medications for the aforementioned diseases or stroke.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par16">Baseline demographic variables, dietary factors, and health indices were compared according to the quartiles of egg consumption. Categorical variables were compared using the chi-square test. For continuous variables, means and standard errors of egg-intake quartiles were compared using the general linear-regression analysis. Multivariable-adjusted means of blood lipid concentrations were compared in association with egg-intake quartiles. Hazard ratios (HR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) were analyzed with Cox proportional hazard regression to examine the CVD incidence by egg-intake quartiles.</p><p id="Par17">Potential confounding factors were based on the results of preliminary analyses and previous literature reviews on the relevant topic. For example, the known risk factors for the main outcome and variables associated with exposure were considered. Moreover, we employed a separate model that was adjusted for variables suspected to be implicated in the causal pathway, e.g., the BMI.</p><p id="Par18">The following models were performed: model 1 was unadjusted; model 2 was adjusted for age, sex, educational level, residential area, monthly household income, alcohol drinking, smoking in pack-years, and physical activity level; Model 3 was adjusted for all covariates included in model 2 plus dietary supplement use, history of hypertension and dyslipidemia, and the intake levels of total energy, vegetables, fruits, fiber, red meat, and vitamin E; and last, model 4 was adjusted for all variables included in model 3 plus BMI. We performed a collinearity test using the variance inflation factor (VIF) and condition index. None of the VIFs exceeded 2.1, and the condition indices did not exceed 3.8.</p><p id="Par19">Multiple potential effect modifiers, including demographic variables, lifestyle factors, and history of medical conditions, were tested using multiplicative interaction terms in the regression model. As a result, a diagnosis of T2DM was determined as an effect modifier of the association between egg intake and CVD incidence. The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend was calculated by using the median of the egg-intake quartiles as a continuous variable. All analyses were performed using the Statistical Analysis System software (version 9.4; SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par20">The participants included in our analysis had similar characteristics as those who were excluded, including their BMI, current smoking status, physical activity level, history of dyslipidemia, and the intake levels of total vegetables, total fruits, red meat, and fiber. However, the included participants were more likely to be younger (odds ratio (OR): 0.96, 95% CI: 0.95–0.97), be men (OR: 1.22, 95% CI: 1.06–1.42), drink alcohol (OR: 1.34, 95% CI: 1.15–1.55), and have a higher educational (OR: 1.81, 95% CI: 1.39–2.37) and monthly household income levels (OR: 2.16, 95% CI: 1.51–3.09). Moreover, they were more likely to have a lower level of vitamin E intake (OR: 0.97, 95% CI: 0.95–0.99), and less likely to use dietary supplements (OR: 0.73, 95% CI: 0.60–0.87) and have a history of hypertension (OR: 0.55, 95% CI: 0.46–0.66; Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par21">During the average follow-up of 7.3 years, 570 incident cases of CVD were identified. The participants’ mean age at baseline was 52.0 ± 0.1 years. The average egg-intake levels were 0.1 ± 0.02, 0.7 ± 0.004, 1.6 ± 0.01, and 4.2 ± 0.04 eggs/week for the first, second, third, and fourth quartiles, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The group with the higher egg intake was younger, included more men, and showed higher educational levels than the group with the lower egg intake (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 for all). Moreover, those with a higher egg intake consumed more vegetables, fruits, red meat, total energy, and dietary supplements (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 for all) than their counterparts.<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and lifestyle characteristics of participants according to quartiles of egg consumption</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Egg-consumption levels</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
<sup>a</sup>
</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q1 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2312)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q2 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2368)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2218)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4 (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 2350)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Age (years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.6 ± 0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.6 ± 0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.7 ± 0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.1 ± 0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Male</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">972 (42.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1178 (49.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1098 (49.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1175 (50.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.6 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.6 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.5 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.5 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Educational level</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  ≤Elementary school or lower</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1066 (46.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">778 (32.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">602 (27.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">596 (25.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Middle school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">573 (25.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">568 (24.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">474 (21.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">503 (21.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  High school</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">509 (22.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">705 (29.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">788 (35.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">804 (34.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  ≥College or higher</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">146 (6.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">311 (13.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (15.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">433 (18.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Residential area</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Ansung</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1526 (66.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1172 (49.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">846 (38.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">997 (42.4)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Ansan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">786 (34.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1196 (50.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1372 (61.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1353 (57.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monthly household income (KRW)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  &lt;1,000,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1080 (47.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">812 (34.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">610 (27.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">673 (29.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  1–&lt;2,000,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">618 (27.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">705 (30.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">662 (30.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">699 (30.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  2–&lt;4,000,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">461 (20.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">648 (27.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">727 (33.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">726 (31.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  ≥4,000,000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">109 (4.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">171 (7.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">189 (8.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">225 (9.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alcohol drinking</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">987 (42.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1138 (48.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1098 (49.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1165 (49.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Smoking (pack-years)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.1 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Physical activity level</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Low</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1227 (55.0)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1433 (62.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1438 (66.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1435 (62.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Middle</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">372 (16.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">371 (16.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">366 (16.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">409 (17.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  High</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">631 (28.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">488 (21.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">358 (16.6)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">439 (19.2)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total energy intake (kJ)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6769.7 ± 47.7</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7280.6 ± 46.9</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7722.4 ± 48.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8470.1 ± 47.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total vegetable intake (serving/week)<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.2 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.0 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.5 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.4 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total fruit intake (serving/week)<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.3 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.2 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.0 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6 ± 0.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Egg intake (serving/week)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1 ± 0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7 ± 0.004</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.6 ± 0.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.2 ± 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Red meat intake (serving/week)<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0 ± 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fiber intake (g/day)<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.3 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.1 ± 0.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Vitamin E intake (mg/day) <sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7 ± 0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dietary supplement use</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">384 (16.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">415 (17.8)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">403 (18.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">527 (22.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">History of disease</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Hypertension</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">446 (19.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">314 (13.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">303 (13.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">304 (12.9)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">  Dyslipidemia</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62 (2.7)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59 (2.5)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52 (2.3)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 (2.1)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are mean ± standard error and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%)</p><p>Q quartile, KRW Korean Republic Won</p><p><sup>a</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values are derived from χ<sup>2</sup> test for categorical variables, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trends is derived from general linear regression for continuous variables</p><p><sup>b</sup> Intake levels were adjusted for total energy intake</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par22">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the participants’ blood lipid concentrations according to egg-intake quartiles. We did not find any significant differences in any of the indicators, including total, HDL-C, LDL-C, and triglyceride levels, in association with egg-intake quartiles.<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Anthropometry and blood lipid profiles according to quartiles of egg consumption</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Egg-consumption levels</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.86 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.80 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.81 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.80 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">HDL-cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22 ± 0.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23 ± 0.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23 ± 0.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23 ± 0.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LDL-cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.88 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.86 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.85 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.84 ± 0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Triglyceride (mmol/L)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.65 ± 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55 ± 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60 ± 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59 ± 0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are mean ± standard error. Adjusted for age, sex, body mass index, educational level, residential area, monthly household income, alcohol drinking, smoking in pack-years, and physical activity level</p><p>Q quartile, HDL high-density lipoprotein, LDL low-density lipoprotein</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents the HRs and 95% CIs of CVD incidence according to egg-intake quartiles. In multivariable-adjusted models, egg-intake levels in quartiles were not associated with incident CVD.<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Hazard ratio (95% confidence interval) for incident CVD risk according to quartiles of egg consumption</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Egg-consumption levels</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Case</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">151</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">170</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">126</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">123</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2312</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2368</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2218</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2350</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Person-years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15801</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18503</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15859</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17197</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.95 (0.76–1.18)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81 (0.64–1.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74 (0.58–0.94)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.94–1.50)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 (0.89–1.46)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (0.80–1.32)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26 (0.99–1.60)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.22 (0.94–1.57)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 (0.86–1.47)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27 (0.99–1.61)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23 (0.95–1.60)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14 (0.87–1.49)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Model 1: unadjusted. Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, educational level, residential area, monthly household income, alcohol drinking, smoking in pack-years, and physical activity level. Model 3: additionally adjusted for dietary supplement use, history of hypertension and dyslipidemia, and the intake levels of total energy, total vegetables, total fruits, red meat, fiber, and vitamin E. Model 4: model 3 plus additionally adjusted for body mass index</p><p>CVD cardiovascular disease, Q quartile</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par24">The association between egg intake and CVD incidence was further analyzed by stratifying the participants by T2DM diagnosis (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). In this analysis, we found a significant effect–modification with a 2.8-fold increase in CVD incidence in participants with T2DM and belonging to the group with the highest egg intake in comparison to those of the group with the lowest egg intake (HR: 2.81, 95% CI: 1.25–6.30); this finding also exhibited a dose–response relationship (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend: 0.02). However, no significant association between egg-intake level and CVD incidence was observed in participants without a T2DM diagnosis (HR: 1.03, 95% CI: 0.77–1.38).<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Hazard ratio (95% confidence interval) for CVD risk according to quartiles of egg consumption stratified by diabetes status at baseline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Egg-consumption levels</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> for trend</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q1</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q2</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q3</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q4</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Diabetes</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Case</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> N</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">184</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">147</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Person-years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1119</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1101</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">877</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">960</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.28 (0.67–2.45)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67 (0.88–3.20)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32 (0.68–2.57)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49 (0.73–3.03)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.37 (1.16–4.83)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.82 (0.89–3.72)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60 (0.76–3.36)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.23 (1.48–7.05)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43 (1.11–5.35)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72 (0.81–3.64)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.70 (1.65–8.30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.81 (1.25–6.30)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Non-diabetes</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Case</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">135</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">148</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">104</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> N</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2128</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2222</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2080</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2203</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Person-years</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12152</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14862</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">12283</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13670</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92 (0.73–1.16)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74 (0.57–0.96)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.69 (0.54–0.90)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13 (0.88–1.45)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04 (0.79–1.36)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94 (0.71–1.23)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.19 (0.93–1.54)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08 (0.82–1.43)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02 (0.76–1.36)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Model 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20 (0.93–1.55)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10 (0.83–1.45)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.03 (0.77–1.38)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Model 1: unadjusted. Model 2: adjusted for age, sex, educational level, residential area, monthly household income, alcohol drinking, smoking in pack-years, and physical activity level. Model 3: additionally adjusted for dietary supplement use, history of hypertension and dyslipidemia, and the intake levels of total energy, total vegetables, total fruits, red meat, fiber, and vitamin E. Model 4: model 3 plus additionally adjusted for body mass index</p><p>CVD cardiovascular disease, Q quartile</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par25">This study prospectively examined the association between egg intake and CVD incidence among Korean adults by analyzing data from the Ansung–Ansan cohort. Overall, higher egg intake was not associated with an increased risk for CVD. However, after stratifying the participants by T2DM status, those with T2DM in the group with the highest egg intake had a 2.8 times higher CVD incidence than those in the group with the lowest egg intake. Conversely, we did not observe this association in participants without T2DM.</p><p id="Par26">Eggs are a well-known nutritious food source that can easily supply inexpensive high-quality protein as well as micronutrients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, egg consumption has been a main cause of health-related concerns because eggs contain a high level of dietary cholesterol and might increase the blood cholesterol level, which is in turn strongly associated with CVD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. However, prior evidence indicates that circulating cholesterols are not only derived from a diet based on animal sources but also synthesized by the liver and other organs in the human body<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Intracellular cholesterol homeostasis is precisely regulated by several physiological mechanisms involved in cholesterol biosynthesis; as such, the effect of high dietary cholesterol intake on the serum cholesterol level may be negligible<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Indeed, no measurable associations between egg-consumption levels and blood lipid profiles were observed in this study. Moreover, as eggs have high contents of antioxidants such as lutein and zeaxanthin, egg consumption might reduce the oxidation of LDL-C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par27">Various dietary guidelines for the general population with different limitations concerning egg consumption and dietary cholesterol intake have been released<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. For example, in 2015, the US Departments of Health and Human Services and Agriculture changed the dietary guideline for egg consumption from limiting egg intake to deleting the limitation altogether, but cautioning individuals to limit the intake of saturated and trans fats<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Several countries do not support the idea that limiting egg intake is an important dietary recommendation for the general population to maintain normal blood cholesterol levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. In Korea, the 2015 Dietary Reference Intake for Koreans does not clearly indicate to limit the intake of major food sources of dietary cholesterol but does recommend to limit the dietary intake of cholesterol to &lt;300 mg/day for the general population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. More specifically, the 2015 Korean guidelines for the management of dyslipidemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> recommend a dietary intake of cholesterol &lt;300 mg/day for patients with dyslipidemia or CVD to avoid excessive cholesterol intake, which is identical to European guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par28">In the present study, the association between egg-consumption quartiles and CVD incidence was modified by T2DM status. Specifically, higher egg consumption was significantly associated with an increased risk for incident CVD among participants with T2DM, whereas no evident association was detected in those without T2DM. This result is in line with several previous studies that showed a positive association between the levels of egg consumption and cardiovascular risk under metabolic conditions such as T2DM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. For example, Hu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> investigated the association between egg-consumption levels (&lt;1, 1, 2–4, 5–6, and 7 eggs/week) and the risk for CVD using the Health Professional Follow-Up Study (men) and Nurses’ Health Study (women) (aged 40–75 and 30–55years old, respectively). They reported that patients with T2DM who consumed ≥1 egg/day had a 2.02 times higher risk for CVD (relative risk: 2.02, 95% CI: 1.05–3.87) than those who consumed &lt;1 egg/week. In addition, the Health, Aging, and Body Composition study conducted among elderly individuals aged 70–79 years showed that, among patients with T2DM, those with the highest egg consumption (≥3 eggs/week) had a 5.02 times higher risk for CVD (HR: 5.02, 95% CI: 1.63–15.51) than those with the lowest egg consumption (&lt;1 egg/week)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">The mechanism by which egg consumption in the diabetic state increases the risk for CVD has not been elucidated, but insulin sensitivity might affect HDL-C metabolism and cholesterol transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Thus, individuals with low insulin sensitivity, such as those with T2DM, might have elevated blood total cholesterol, very-low-density lipoprotein, and LDL-C levels when compared to the general population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>; this cluster is associated with an increased risk for CVD. Moreover, patients with T2DM may have decreased levels of apolipoprotein E and increased levels of apolipoprotein C3, resulting in abnormal cholesterol transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par30">The dietary guidelines regarding egg and dietary cholesterol consumption for patients with T2DM vary between countries. For example, the Australian National Heart Foundation recommends a maximum intake of six eggs/week for both healthy individuals and those with T2DM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, whereas US guidelines have maintained a restriction on dietary cholesterol intake for diabetes patients, recommending that dietary cholesterol intake be limited to &lt;300 mg/day (one egg contains about 200 mg of cholesterol) and &lt;4 eggs/week<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The Korean Diabetes Association recommends a dietary cholesterol intake of &lt;300 mg/day, which is identical to the dietary guideline for the general Korean population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Our data support dietary cholesterol restrictions for Korean patients with T2DM but not for healthy individuals.</p><p id="Par31">This study has several limitations. There might be residual confounding due to unknown or unmeasured factors in this cohort study despite the adjustments for multiple lifestyle and dietary factors that are known to be associated with CVD risk. Information on how the eggs were prepared was not collected; thus, it was not possible to evaluate the specific effect of egg consumption on the health outcome based on the cooking method. Despite these limitations, this study has several strengths, including the analysis of prospective cohort data that revealed an association between diet and disease in a prospective manner. Two repeat SQFFQs were used to reduce the error associated with the dietary survey method. Finally, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first prospective analysis on the association between egg consumption and CVD incidence conducted in the Korean population; thus, the study results are a useful scientific evidence for establishing dietary guidelines on cholesterol intake for the general Korean population and patients with T2DM who need dyslipidemia management.</p><p id="Par32">In conclusion, we prospectively observed that high egg consumption might increase CVD risk in patients with T2DM in a large cohort study of Korean adults. Further investigations on the association between egg consumption and CVD risk and mortality are needed through large-scale RCTs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec10"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41387_2018_33_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary table 1 Odds of being included in the final analysis</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41387_2018_33_MOESM2_ESM.pptx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary figure 1 Flowchart depicting the inclusion process of the study participants</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41387-018-0033-1.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Data in this study were from the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study (KoGES; 4851-302), National Research Institute of Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and Ministry for Health and Welfare, Republic of Korea. This research was supported by the Basic Science Research Program, through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Science, Information and Communications Technology and Future Planning (NRF-2017R1A1A3A04069759), and the Ministry of Education, Science, and Technology (NRF-2015R1A2A1A15054758).</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p id="Par33">J.J. conducted statistical analysis and wrote the draft of the manuscript. M.J.S. and O.Y.K. wrote the draft of the manuscript, contributed to the discussion, and reviewed the final manuscript, and K.P. developed the study design, supervised the analysis, wrote the manuscript, and reviewed the final manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar2"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="Par34">The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weed</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of egg consumption and risk of coronary heart disease and stroke</article-title><source>J. Am. Coll. Nutr.</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07315724.2016.1152928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27710205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prospective study of egg consumption and risk of cardiovascular disease in men and women</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1999</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>1387</fpage><lpage>1394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.281.15.1387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10217054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Egg consumption and risk of coronary heart disease and stroke: dose-response meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2013</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>e8539</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e8539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23295181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3538567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Djousse</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaziano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Egg consumption in relation to cardiovascular disease and mortality: the Physicians’ Health Study</article-title><source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</source><year>2008</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>964</fpage><lpage>969</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/87.4.964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18400720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2386667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McCane, R. A. &amp; Widdowson, E. M. McCance and Widdowson’s The Composition of Foods, 6 ed., 125–129 (The Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge and the Food Standards Agency: London, 2002).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weggemans</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zock</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary cholesterol from eggs increases the ratio of total cholesterol to high-density lipoprotein cholesterol in humans: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</source><year>2001</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/73.5.885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11333841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Egg consumption in relation to risk of cardiovascular disease and diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</source><year>2013</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.112.051318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23676423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3683816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of egg consumption on cardiovascular risk factors in individuals with Type 2 diabetes and at risk for developing diabetes: a systematic review of randomized nutritional intervention studies</article-title><source>Can. J. Diabetes</source><year>2017</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjd.2016.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28359773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-sectional and longitudinal associations between egg consumption and metabolic syndrome in adults ≥40 years old: The Yangpyeong Cohort of the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study (KoGES_Yangpyeong)</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0147729</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26808174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4726710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lajous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Egg consumption and risk of incident type 2 diabetes: a dose–response meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies</article-title><source>Br. J. Nutr.</source><year>2016</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>2212</fpage><lpage>2218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S000711451600146X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27108219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cohort profile: The Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study (KoGES) Consortium</article-title><source>Int. J. Epidemiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>e20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyv316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27085081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5837648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention Korea National Institute of Health. Manual of Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study (Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention Korea National Institute of Health, 2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stampfer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Total energy intake: implications for epidemiologic analyses</article-title><source>Am. J. Epidemiol.</source><year>1986</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a114366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3521261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation and reproducibility of food frequency questionnaire for Korean genome epidemiologic study</article-title><source>Eur. J. Clin. Nutr.</source><year>2007</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1435</fpage><lpage>1441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17299477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compendium of physical activities: classification of energy costs of human physical activities</article-title><source>Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.</source><year>1993</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/00005768-199301000-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8292105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization.</collab></person-group><source>The Asia-Pacific perspective: redefining obesity and its treatment</source><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Health Communications Australia</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO expert consultation.</collab></person-group><article-title>Appropriate body-mass index for Asian populations and its implications for policy and intervention strategies</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2004</year><volume>363</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)15268-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14726171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>QUINTÃO</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>GRUNDY</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary cholesterol on the regulation of total body cholesterol in man</article-title><source>J. Lipid Res.</source><year>1971</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5108133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecerf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Lorgeril</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary cholesterol: from physiology to cardiovascular risk</article-title><source>Br. J. Nutr.</source><year>2011</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114511000237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21385506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribaya-Mercado</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lutein and zeaxanthin and their potential roles in disease prevention</article-title><source>J. Am. Coll. Nutr.</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>567s</fpage><lpage>587ss</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07315724.2004.10719427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15640510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSalvo</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casavale</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary guidelines for americans</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2016</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.18396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26746707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services and U.S. Department of Agriculture.</collab></person-group><source>2015–2020 Dietary Guidelines for Americans</source><year>2015</year><edition>8 ed</edition><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services and U.S. Department of Agriculture</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministry of Health and Welfare and The Korean Nutrition Society.</collab></person-group><source>Dietary Reference Intakes for Koreans 2015</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Sejong</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ministry of Health and Welfare</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolonel</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary intakes and health-related behaviours of Korean American women born in the USA and Korea: the Multiethnic Cohort Study</article-title><source>Public. Health Nutr.</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PHN2005740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16277807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Committee for the Korean Guidelines for the Management of Dyslipidemia.</collab></person-group><article-title>2015 Korean guidelines for the management of dyslipidemia: executive summary (English Translation)</article-title><source>Korean Circ. J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4070/kcj.2016.46.3.275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27275165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4891593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ESC/EAS Guidelines for the management of dyslipidaemias: the task force for the management of dyslipidaemias of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Atherosclerosis Society (EAS)</article-title><source>Eur. Heart J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1769</fpage><lpage>1818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehr158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21712404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dietary fat and cholesterol and risk of cardiovascular disease in older adults: the Health ABC Study</article-title><source>Nutr. Metab. Cardiovasc. Dis.</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.numecd.2009.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20338738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2911502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riemens</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Tol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stulp</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dullaart</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of insulin sensitivity and the TaqIB cholesteryl ester transfer protein gene polymorphism on plasma lecithin:cholesterol acyltransferase and lipid transfer protein activities and their response to hyperinsulinemia in non-diabetic men</article-title><source>J. Lipid Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1467</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10428983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reaven</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of apolipoprotein E in the plasma of insulin-dependent and noninsulin-dependent diabetics and its relation to cholesterol net transport</article-title><source>J. Lipid Res.</source><year>1986</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1052</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3794549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imrie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apo C subclasses from non-insulin-dependent diabetic patients–a quantitative comparison with control subjects</article-title><source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source><year>1995</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>278s</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bst023278s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7672305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Heart Foundation of Australia. <italic toggle="yes">Position statement: dietary fats and dietary cholesterol for cardiovascular health</italic>. (National Heart Foundation (NHF), Australia, 2009).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>