<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">797</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-id">0405376</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7942123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7942123.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7942123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7942123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33595497</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijo.IJO_253_20</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJO-69-661</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Special Focus on Diabetic Retinopathy, Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dietary associations with diabetic retinopathy—A cohort study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadri</surname><given-names initials="R">Rajani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vishwanath</surname><given-names initials="P">Prithvi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parameshwar</surname><given-names initials="D">Devika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names initials="S">Sudhir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudva</surname><given-names initials="AA">Ajay A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Ophthalmology, A. J. Institute of Medical Sciences and Research Centre, Mangalore, Karnataka, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr. Rajani Kadri, Department of Ophthalmology, A. J. Institute of Medical Sciences and Research Centre, Mangalore - 575 004, Karnataka, India. E-mail: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="rajani.kadri@gmail.com">rajani.kadri@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>69</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">376992</issue-id><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-03 01:25:15.480"><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2021 Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncsalicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="IJO-69-661.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Purpose:</title><p>To assess the role of dietary factors in the development of diabetic retinopathy (DR) in diabetics.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Methods:</title><p>This prospective study was carried out on patients attending the outpatient department of ophthalmology for a period of 1 year. An interview-based 24-hour diet recall was used to document average daily dietary nutrient intakes. Each patient was subjected to a comprehensive ocular examination to look for DR.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>A total of 261 patients attending the outpatient department of ophthalmology were the participants for this study. The mean (±SD) age of the participants was 57.73 ± 11.29 years, and 67% were men. One hundred and six participants had DR. Univariate analysis revealed sex, duration, fish (times/week), egg (yes/no), rice lunch (yes/no), rice dinner, rice (boiled/white), and total calorie intake to be associated with DR (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Logistic regression multivariable analysis revealed males (OR: 3.20, 95% CI: 1.65–6.19), longer duration of diabetes (OR:1.05,95% CI:1.01-1.11), antioxidant intake (OR: 3.42, 95% CI: 1.65–7.05), and consumption of rice (OR: 3.19, 95% CI: 1.17–8.69) to have significant association with DR (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), with the odds of developing DR increasing three times in these patients. The odds of developing DR were lesser with more frequent (&gt;2 times/week) fish consumption (OR: 0.42, 95% CI: 0.18–0.94) and in patients on pharmacological treatment for diabetes mellitus (OR: 0.16, 95% CI: 0.04–0.58). Binary logistic regression revealed chapathi consumption (OR: 9.37, 95% CI: 1.64–53.68) to be associated with severe forms and fish consumption (OR: 0.06, 95% CI: 0.01–1.06) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) to be associated with less severe forms of DR.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Males, longer duration of diabetes, antioxidant intake, fish consumption, and consumption of rice were associated with the occurrence of DR. Participants with diabetes who consumed fish more frequently and those who were on pharmacological treatment for diabetes mellitus had a significantly lower risk of DR and frequent fish consumption could reduce the risk of DR progression.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Diabetes mellitus</kwd><kwd>diabetic retinopathy</kwd><kwd>diet</kwd><kwd>fish</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-SA</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is one of the leading causes of blindness among the working-class individuals around the world.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Numerous risk factors that contribute to the progression of DR have been identified. Metabolic control and duration of diabetes were found to be strong risk factors.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] It is regarded as a microvascular disease, but retinal neurodegeneration is also involved. Complex interrelated pathophysiological mechanisms triggered by hyperglycemia underlie the development of DR. These mechanisms include genetic and epigenetic factors, increased production of free radicals, advanced glycosylation end products, inflammatory factors, and vascular endothelial growth factor. Optimal control of blood glucose and blood pressure in individuals with diabetes remains the cornerstone for preventing the development and arresting the progression of DR.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p><p>Control of blood glucose has been achieved either by diet control or medications. Although diet is an established factor in the development of diabetes, its role in the development and progression of DR needs further investigation.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] While there may be several dietary guidelines for the management of diabetes in general, diet-specific guidelines for the prevention, retardation, and management of microvascular complications of diabetes such as DR are not available.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</p><p>Few studies have emphasized the role of certain micronutrients and food groups in the possible pathomechanism of DR.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Protective role of fish and fruits on DR onset and progression has been determined in some previous studies.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] However, a more comprehensive study addressing the role of dietary pattern and various food groups is necessary to help fill the void in the existing information in the subject. Dietary patterns vary globally. In our coastal belt, people consume oily fish and rice, especially parboiled variety as the staple diet. We aimed at conducting a comprehensive assessment of the dietary associations with DR.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Methods</title><p>A one-year prospective institutional study was conducted on 261 patients attending the outpatient department of ophthalmology. Prior approval for conducting this study was obtained from the Institutional Review Board, and all study procedures were adhered to recommendations of the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained from each participant.</p><p>The present study included all consenting patients aged 30 years and above who were diagnosed as diabetic at least 1 year before the study. The presence of diabetes was defined as physician diagnosed diabetes, with the information retrieved from participant's case notes, and excluded all nondiabetic patients. Three hundred and twenty-six consenting participants were interviewed on 24-hour diet recall. Sixty-five participants with incomplete information, type 1 DM, and coexisting ocular disease were excluded ending up with 261 participants for analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> shows the consort flow diagram of selection of study participants).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram showing the selection of study participants</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="IJO-69-661-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Dietary variables in this study were obtained by structured interviews with participants on 24-h diet recall. It was administered twice nonconsecutively to each participant. Less frequently consumed food was further questioned and documented as weekly consumption. The average daily calorie intake was calculated based on calorific values of individual components.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Consumption of meat and fish were reported as times per week. Egg consumption was recorded as to whether or not consumed daily. Milk, tea, and coffee consumption were reported as the number of glasses per day and fruit consumption as the number of serves per day (a serve = 1 medium piece or 2 small pieces of fruit or 1 cup of diced pieces). Breakfast preference (depending on the items most commonly consumed by this population— idli, dosa, upma, jola roti) was also noted. Further, consumption of rice and preference for white rice or parboiled, chapathi and the predominant meal at dinner (rice or chapathi) were also taken into consideration. Additionally, we also enquired about the intake of antioxidants and the modality of treatment for diabetes—oral hypoglycemic agents, insulin therapy, combination therapy, or dietary modification alone. Glycated hemoglobin and fasting blood sugar were also recorded.</p><p>The following baseline variables were also documented in the present study: demographic factors like age, gender, family history of diabetes, diabetes duration, and lifestyle factors (smoking and alcohol drinking). The ocular examination included slit-lamp anterior segment examination, and a dilated fundus examination using slit-lamp biomicroscopy (90D), indirect ophthalmoscopy to look for DR, and fundus photography.</p><p>The primary outcome variable studied was DR and the secondary outcome studied was the severity of DR. The independent variables include demographic factors, treatment, and dietary factors. Demographic factors included age, sex, duration, smoking, alcohol consumption, and family history. Treatment included antioxidant intake and treatment with oral hypoglycemic agents, insulin, or dietary control. Dietary factors included breakfast meal, milk, coffee, tea intake, fruit, meat, rice, chapathi, egg, and fish.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The data were checked for its distribution by Anderson Darling test. Statistical analysis was performed using Minitab<sup>®</sup> 17.1.0.</p><p>All data will be presented as numerical or categorical data. Numerical data are presented with a mean (SD), median with IQR, and categorical data with proportions. Univariate analysis was attempted using Chi square or fisher exact test for categorical variables influencing the DR. Univariate analysis with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values&lt;0.1 was considered for significance and those predictors were included in multivariate analysis.</p><p>Binary logistic regression analysis was used to find out the associations between DR and factors influencing it. The logit link function, the calculated odds ratio (OR), and a 95% confidence interval (CI) for the OR were considered to determine whether the association between the response events and the predictors is statistically significant with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> ≤ 0.05 (adjusted P, P/number of predictors in the model). Predictors included in the final model were age, sex, duration, antioxidants (yes/no), pharmacological treatment, egg (yes/no), fish (more frequent [&gt;2 times/week]/less frequent), chapathi (yes/no), and rice (yes/no). The model was assessed with <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup> values and the goodness-of-fit tests with Hosmer–Lemeshow <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values. The variance inflation factor (VIF) was checked for multicollinearity. If VIF values were found high for any predictors, such predictor was excluded from the final model. A positive coefficient and an OR greater than 1 would indicate a high chance of DR, when correlated with a specific predictor.</p><p>A binary logistic regression analysis was used to find out the associations between severity of DR and predictors. The severity was described as presence (severe NPDR, PDR) of or absence (mild, moderate NPDR) of severe forms of DR. Predictors included in the model were age, duration, antioxidant (yes/no), fish (yes/no), chapathi (yes/no), and rice (yes/no). The final model fit was checked with log-likelihood values and goodness-of-fit <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value (both Pearson and Deviance). The ability of predictability was checked using Somers' <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> values. A negative coefficient and an OR lesser than 1 would indicate protection against DR correlated with a specific predictor. All primary and secondary outcomes were compared using a conventional α level of 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><p>The mean (±SD) age of participants was 57.73 ± 11.29 years, and 67% were men. One hundred and six (40.6%) participants had DR. Fifty (47%) had mild nonproliferative DR (NPDR), 41 (38.6%) had moderate NPDR, 12 (12.2%) had severe NPDR, and 3 (2.8%) had PDR. Univariate analysis showing the association between each food group and DR is presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Sex, duration, HBA1c, antioxidant, meat (times/week), fish (times/week), egg (yes/no), rice lunch (yes/no), rice dinner (yes/no), rice (parboiled/white), and total calorie were significantly associated with DR (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). No significant association was observed between occurrence of DR and any of the following variables: smoking, alcohol, hypertension, and family history, consumption of milk, coffee, tea, and breakfast meal.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Univariate associations between predictors and diabetic retinopathy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predictors</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presence of DR (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=106)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of DR (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=155)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;40 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (8.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 41-70 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (80.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (81.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;70 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (13.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (9.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (23.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (39.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (76.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (60.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 1-10 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (66.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (80)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;10 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (34.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (10.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.298</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (16.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (19.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.493</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (21.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (20)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (34.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (34.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.884</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antioxidant</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (30.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (12.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pharmacological treatment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (81.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (97.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (18.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Milk (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (3.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (8.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.717</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tea (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (77.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (78.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.893</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Coffee (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (11.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (7.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.326</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fruits (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (42.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (39.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.617</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Meat (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (50.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72 (46.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.476</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fish (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (50.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (56.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.409</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Egg (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (21.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (10.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Chapathi (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (31.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (40.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rice lunch (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (92.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (78.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rice dinner (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (80.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (65.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rice boiled/white</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (77.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (60.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rice (yes/no)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (92.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (78.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total calories</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;500</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 500-1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (44.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (51.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (52.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 (45.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are represented as number (percentage). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> values were obtained using Fisher’s exact test or Chi-square tests as appropriate</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> details the results of multivariate regression analysis of various predictors with DR. It shows no association between occurrence of any grade of DR with age (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.981). After adjusting for other factors that were tested, increased risk of developing DR is associated with longer duration of DR (OR: 1.05, 95% CI: 1.01–1.11) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014), males (OR: 3.20, 95% CI: 1.65–6.19) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), consumption of antioxidant (OR: 3.42, 95% CI: 1.65–7.05) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001), and consumption of rice (OR: 3.19, 95% CI: 1.17–8.69) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018). Diabetics on pharmacological treatment (insulin and oral hypoglycemic agents) (OR: 0.16, 95% CI: 0.04–0.58) compared to those on diet control and diabetics consuming fish more frequently (&gt;2 times/week) (OR: 0.42, 95% CI: 0.18–0.94) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.030) were at less risk of developing DR. Consumption of egg and <italic toggle="yes">chapathi</italic> were not associated with the occurrence of DR.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Multivariate regression analysis for occurrence of diabetic retinopathy (of any severity) versus various risk factors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=261)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Predictors</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antioxidant</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharmacological treatment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of rice</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.69</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of chapathi</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.898</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of egg</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.451</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of fish</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> More frequent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.422</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less frequent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>OR=Odds ratio, CI=Confidence intervals; adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was used for statistical significance</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> summarizes the results of binary logistic regression analysis of various predictors with severity of DR. Participants consuming antioxidants (OR: 0.08, 95% CI: 0.01–0.95) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001) were at less risk of progressing to severe forms of DR. More frequent consumption of fish (OR: 0.06, 95% CI: 0.01–1.06) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.028) was associated with less severe forms of DR and a protective effect on the eye. Chapathi (OR: 9.37, 95% CI: 1.64–53.68) consumption was significantly associated with severe forms of DR. This finding in our study needs to be interpreted with caution as there is a general tendency for diet switchover to chapathis with increased severity of the disease in our subset of population.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Multivariate regression analysis for severity of diabetic retinopathy versus various risk factors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=106)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Predictors</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">OR</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antioxidant</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of rice</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of chapathi</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consumption of fish</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> More frequent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Less frequent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>OR=Odds ratio, CI=Confidence intervals; adjusted <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value was used for statistical significance</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Dietary modification is a simple and achievable measure in the holistic management of diabetes and its microvascular complications in diabetic patients. To the best of our knowledge, ours is the first study of its kind ventured in our country to provide a comprehensive analysis of the association of food groups with DR. The influence of various dietary components in the development of DR among a sizeable proportion of indigenous population living in the coastal belt of South India has been discussed in the current study. We report that participants with longer duration of diabetes, male gender, antioxidants supplementation, patients on pharmacological treatment, consumption of fish, and rice consumption had an association with DR. Consuming fish and antioxidant intake had a significantly lower risk of DR progression. Meanwhile, no direct association of consumption of fruits, meat, milk, tea, and breakfast type with DR could be ascertained from our observations.</p><p>Refined grains such as white rice and refined wheat have become staples of the modern Asian Indian diet. Shobhana <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] in their study showed that as wheat based formulations yield lower glycemic indices than rice-based ones, wheat based formulations as a food supplement or a meal replacer in diabetic subjects were more suitable than rice- based formulations. However in our study chapathi (wheat based) intake was significantly associated with severe forms of DR. We speculate that this finding could be attributed to the fact that in India uncontrolled diabetics often take to consuming chapathis largely in their diet. Though the nutritional value and safety of consuming either rice or chapathi in diabetics have been debated for decades, parboiled rice, because of its increased fiber content, high nutrition value, and low glycemic index compared to white rice, has been claimed to be good for diabetic patients.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Parboiled rice is the preferred grain by South Indians. The majority of the participants in our study also consumed parboiled rice (67%). Odds of development and progression of DR increased significantly in the subjects consuming rice. Though parboiled rice has been considered to be superior to white rice, the quantity of consumption is often ignored. As the serving sizes of food preparation are not paid attention, individuals consume far more calories than they realize. Increased quantity of consumption of rice or chapathi can be detrimental for diabetics. High calorie intake was significantly associated with DR in our study. Wong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. in a systematic review also suggested the possibility of association of high total caloric intake with greater DR risk.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</p><p>In the present study, we observed an inverse association between more frequent (&gt;2 times/week) fish consumption and DR progression. Seafood is a very important constituent of the staple diet among the coastal population. In our study, consumption of fatty fish such as mackerel, sardines, croaker fish, and silver fish showed a decreased likelihood of developing DR changes in the study participants. Fish intake had a significant protective effect on a diabetic eye. Recently two large studies,[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] one on Spanish adults and one on Asian population, showed that at least two servings of oily fish per week had a significantly lower risk of vision-threatening DR. Similarity of finding in two different ethnic groups may suggest a biological association between fish intake and DR as suggested by Chua <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</p><p>Fruits are known to be low-glycemic-index foods rich in dietary fiber, which can slow down the conversion of carbohydrates into glucose after ingestion. Mahoney <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. concluded that more frequent consumption of foods rich in flavonoid particularly fruits like citrus fruit, apples, berries, and dark green leafy vegetables was associated with reduced odds of having DR.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] However, we failed to find any association of fruit with DR; this could be attributed to the smaller number of subjects consuming fruits in our study.</p><p>Even though egg consumption was reported as a risk factor for diabetes mellitus in previous studies, it was not associated with the risk of DR in this study. While there is little or no evidence of the role of eggs on the development of DR, many studies have tried to explain its association with diabetes. Djousse <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] have demonstrated that daily consumption of at least one egg is associated with a greater risk of type 2 diabetes in both men and women, independently of traditional risk factors for type 2 diabetes. The observed relation between egg intake and diabetes may be partially explained by the cholesterol content of eggs. However, besides dietary cholesterol, eggs contain other important nutrients that have been shown to increase (i.e., saturated fat and cholesterol) or decrease (i.e., polyunsaturated fat) the risk of type 2 diabetes.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] This explains why it could be difficult to assign a protective or deleterious label to the inclusion of eggs in the diet of diabetics.</p><p>A beneficial effect of key antioxidant nutrients was hypothesized based on the consideration that oxidative stress may contribute to microvascular pathology, thereby promoting DR.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] Epidemiologic studies have reported that diets rich in antioxidants such as vitamin C, vitamin E, α-tocopherol, or β-carotene exhibit beneficial effects on glucose metabolism and diabetes prevention.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] However, Davis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. showed that while antioxidants like vitamin C, E, and β-carotene may be protective for other ophthalmic conditions like cataract and age-related macular degeneration, it had no beneficial effect on the prevalence and severity of DR.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] As these antioxidant preparations contain a combination of many micronutrients, doses of which vary, increase or decrease of the dose of micronutrients can result in an inadequate result on DR. Odds of developing DR increased three times in patients on antioxidant supplementation in our study. This significant positive association between supplementation of antioxidants and DR can be attributed to the fact that antioxidant supplementation in our setup was often prescribed to patients who develop early retinal changes, considering the financial constraints and the socioeconomic status of the patient. Majority of our patients who received antioxidant preparation (β-carotene, copper, manganese, selenium, zinc, vitamin C, vitamin E, lutein) had mild-to-moderate grade of DR at baseline. However, antioxidant supplementation was associated inversely with DR progression after adjusting for other confounders in this study, indicating a protective effect on diabetic retina. Further research is needed to better understand this beneficial effect of antioxidants in DR.</p><p>Yan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. showed that consumption of red meat was not associated with the risk of progression of DR. They have also suggested that poultry intake may have a protective role.[<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] The benefits of the intake of milk and other dairy products on retinal vasculature have been highlighted in a study conducted by Gopinath <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] which concluded that participants who consumed five serves or less per week (i.e., 0.75 serves/day) of total dairy products had wider retinal venular caliber. However, we did not find any significant benefit on the retina of diabetic patients conferred by consuming meat, milk, and milk products in our study; this may be due to the fact that&lt;50% of the participants consumed these products.</p><p>Strength and limitations: Inclusion of multiple food groups and data collection on energy intake is the major strength of our study. Small sample size is the major limitation of our study. Other limitations, including recall bias regarding dietary consumption, lifestyle factors like physical activity, and body mass index that could be confounding factors in nutritional research, were also not considered. Finally, as there is variation in the dietary pattern globally; our results can be extrapolated only in an area with similar diet patterns.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, males, longer duration of the disease, antioxidant supplementation, fish, and rice consumption had an association with DR. Consumption of fish had a significantly lower risk of DR, whereas rice consumption was a significant risk factor for DR. Antioxidant supplementation and fish consumption posed a significant lower risk of DR progression. Hence, a restricted balanced diet can substantially help in preventing DR changes. However, further studies are essential to derive a cause–effect relationship between food and DR. Formulating proper dietary guidelines should be the next direction of research in this field.</p><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to acknowledge the assistance of Dr. Thrivikrama Padur Tantry, Professor and HOD, Department of Anaesthesiology, A.J. Institute of Medical Sciences and Research Centre, Mangalore, for statistical analysis.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview of epidemiologic studies of diabetic retinopathy</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Epidemiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17896294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09286580701396720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Porta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjoelie</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rottiers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veglio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for progression to proliferative diabetic retinopathy in the EURODIAB Prospective Complications Study</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>2203</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11793022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s001250100030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetic retinopathy</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>16012</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27159554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrdp.2016.12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhazmi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McEvoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The association between dietary patterns and type 2 diabetes: A systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies</article-title><source>J Hum Nutr Diet</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24102939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jhn.12139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwingshackl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaimani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechthold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>StelmachMardas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Food groups and risk of chronic disease: A protocol for a systematic review and network metaanalysis of cohort studies</article-title><source>Syst Rev</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27460907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13643-016-0302-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4962508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Standards of medical care in diabetes--2013</collab><article-title>American Diabetes Association</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S11</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23264422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc13-S011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3537269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarthy</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidants and diabetic retinopathy</article-title><source>Curr Diab Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23649947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11892-013-0384-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol and eye diseases</article-title><source>Surv Ophthalmol</source><year>2008</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18929762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.survophthal.2008.06.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CTC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gayton</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beulens</surname><given-names>JWJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micronutrients and diabetic retinopathy. A systematic review</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ophtha.2009.06.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19900709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>MFF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamoureux</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Relationship of Dietary Fish Intake and Diabetic Retinopathy in Asian Patients with Type 2 Diabetes.Invest</article-title><source>Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>4284</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loprinzi</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of flavonoid-rich fruit and vegetable intake on diabetic retinopathy and diabetes-related biomarkers</article-title><source>J Diabetes Complications</source><year>2014</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>767</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25055729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2014.06.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elizabeth</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nutrition and Child Development</source><year>2010</year><edition>4th ed</edition><publisher-name>Paras Medical Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shobana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malleshi</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycemic response of rice, wheat and finger millet based diabetic food formulations in normoglycemic subjects</article-title><source>Int J Food Sci Nutr</source><year>2007</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17558728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09637480701252229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parboiled rice metabolism differs in healthy and diabetic individuals with similar improvement in glycemic response</article-title><source>Nutrition</source><year>2018</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29429534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.nut.2017.09.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>MYZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>REK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenwick</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dam</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dietary intake and diabetic retinopathy: A systematic review</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0186582</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0186582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5764236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sala-Vila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Díaz-López</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valls-Pedret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cofán</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García-Layana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamuela-Raventós</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dietary marine omega-3 fatty acids and incident sight-threatening retinopathy in middle-aged and older individuals with type 2 diabetes: Prospective investigation from the PREDIMED trial</article-title><source>JAMA ophthalmol</source><year>2016</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>1142</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27541690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaophthalmol.2016.2906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Djoussé</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaziano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buring</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Egg consumption and risk of type 2 diabetes in men and women</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2009</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/dc08-1271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2628696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stampfer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rimm</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dietary fat intake and risk of type 2 diabetes in women</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2001</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11382654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajcn/73.6.1019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buring</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A prospective study of red meat consumption and type 2 diabetes in middle-aged and elderly women: The women's health study</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2108</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15333470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diacare.27.9.2108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kushi</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Folsom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary fat and incidence of type 2 diabetes in older Iowa women</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1528</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11522694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diacare.24.9.1528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnlöv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zethelius</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riserus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vessby</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum and dietary beta-carotene and alpha-tocopherol and incidence of type 2 diabetes mellitus in a community-based study of Swedish men: Report from the Uppsala Longitudinal Study of Adult Men (ULSAM) study</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>2009</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18985315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00125-008-1189-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyagawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beneficial effects of antioxidants in diabetes: Possible protection of pancreatic beta-cells against glucose toxicity</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>1999</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>2398</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10580429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2337/diabetes.48.12.2398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer-Davis</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reboussin</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamman</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant nutrient intake and diabetic retinopathy: The San Luis Valley Diabetes Study</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><year>1998</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>2264</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9855158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0161-6420(98)91227-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Does daily dietary intake affect diabetic retinopathy progression? 10-year results from the 45 and up study</article-title><source>Br J Ophthalmol</source><year>2019</year><month>2</month><day>22</day><fpage>ii</fpage><comment>bjophthalmol-2018-312990</comment><comment>doi: 10.1136/bjophthalmol-2018-312990</comment><comment>Epub ahead of print</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bjophthalmol-2018-312990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30796056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gopinath</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flood</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burlutsky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lower dairy products and calcium intake is associated with adverse retinal vascular changes in older adults</article-title><source>Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24418384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.numecd.2013.06.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>